<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vindication of the dead: or, six hours reflections upon the six weeks labour in answering Mr. Ashton's Speech published by authority</title>
            <author>Lawton, Charlwood, 1660-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49825</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L739E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221695</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832968</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832968</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37443</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49825)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37443)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2188:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vindication of the dead: or, six hours reflections upon the six weeks labour in answering Mr. Ashton's Speech published by authority</title>
                  <author>Lawton, Charlwood, 1660-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Charlwood Lawton.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>In response to Fowler, Edward. An ansvver to the paper delivered by Mr Ashton at his execution to SirFrancis Child: Sheriff of London.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Lincoln's Inn Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fowler, Edward, 1632-1714. --  Ansvver to the paper delivered by Mr Ashton at his execution to Sir Francis Child: Sheriff of London --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ashton, John, d. 1691 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37443:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE VINDICATION OF THE DEAD: OR, Six Hours Reflections upon the Six Weeks Labour in Anſwering Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Speech publiſhed by Authority.</head>
            <p>§ 1. THE Caſe of Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi> was indeed ſo hard, and his Speech ſo handſom, that I don't won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee a Secretary's <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> for Printing an evaſive, trifling, and malicious Paper, that endeavours to load his Perſon, and blaſt his Writings; but the <hi>Subject</hi> will bear no more, and the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſtands in need of a <hi>Defence.</hi> However I can't but wonder the late Anſwerer ſhould expect to perſwade the World it was not his; becauſe he who profeſſes himſelf an <hi>illiterate Man, and unskill'd in the Laws,</hi> uſes the Terms of <hi>Impending, Prevaricating, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> and <hi>Conſequence,</hi> (two of which are not Terms of <hi>Art,</hi> none of the <hi>Law;</hi> and thoſe other two, that are <hi>Logical,</hi> made familiar to all thoſe that have ever had any ſort of <hi>Breeding</hi> or <hi>Converſation</hi>) for all that is ſaid of this Nature, both at the Beginning and End of the Anſwer, will appear very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to any one that reads his Tryal, even as it is thought fit to be publiſhed; wherein ſome Things have been omitted, as well as others amended, to make it fit for peruſal: For in that he defends himſelf ſo ſenſibly, that it provoked the L. Ch. Juſt. <hi>Pol</hi>— to rage, and ſufficiently proved himſelf capable to write ſuch a Paper; whoſe natural Parts were ſo very ſtrong, and ſo well improved. And if he was ſo well ſatisfied that thoſe that Comply with, as well as thoſe that Support the preſent <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> are Guilty of <hi>Perjury,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with <hi>Rebels,</hi> it very well became the Charity of a dying Man to warn thoſe he left behind him to <hi>Repent;</hi> and if the Words of dying Men have generally more Weight, and make deeper Impreſſions, he did but his duty to recommend to thoſe who ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd him, <hi>Amendment</hi> and <hi>Reſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 2. As for thoſe Matters of Law, which he thought hard in his <hi>Tryal.</hi> I believe he neither complained of, nor deſired any thing, but what the <hi>Lord Chief Juſtice</hi> Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexfen, <hi>Sir</hi> Francis Child, <hi>Mr.</hi> Herbert, and almoſt every Man upon his <hi>Jury,</hi> as well as <hi>Tremain,</hi> and all the other <hi>Council,</hi> would have Cenſured, or thought fit to be Granted in any other Reign: But by this we ſee they have learnt to practiſe thoſe Methods of Tryal which themſelves formerly complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, as Arbitrary and Illegal; and have borrowed Law from the Tories, while to make them Amends they have taught them their Goſpel. I muſt confeſs I know nothing could have ſeemed to warrant the late Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Proceedings ſo well as a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our former ill Meaſures, and proved, that that, and not private Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37443:2"/>was the true Motive of the Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. It cannot be denied but we are poorer of late than formerly, and if the evil In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the late Reigns are fit to be our Miniſters under this, and what was Male-Adminiſtration then commences juſt and neceſſary Politicks now, we ſhall too cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and too ſoon be miſerable; if they don't change Things, you are little the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for changing the Men: The hardſhip and inequality of <hi>Tryals,</hi> and Innovations upon the <hi>Rights</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> in that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, made a very ſpecious Head of the <hi>Prince of</hi> Orange<hi>'s Declaration;</hi> and it is one of the Articles of our new Original Contract, that the Subjects ſhall be free from ſuch Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens: But yet our Judges are in the beaten Road of Arbitrary Power, and can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing contrary to thoſe bleſſed Precedents; and though it was great, and the ſelf-denial of a dying Chriſtian in Mr. <hi>Aſhton,</hi> not to name the <hi>L. Ch. Juſt.</hi> P. and Mr. <hi>H.</hi> for fear of tranſgreſſing that Law of Chriſt of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving Enemies, yet it is to be hoped that ſome <hi>Parliament</hi> will mark them down to Poſterity for Examples ſake; I am ſure I wiſh them no Puniſhment, but what may be neceſſary to keep a <hi>Judg</hi> (who ought to be the <hi>Priſoner's Council</hi>) from being an Advocate againſt him; and a <hi>Jury-man</hi> from <hi>Party</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> where Life and Death. are concerned.</p>
            <p>§ 3. What Mr. <hi>H.</hi> did is thought ſo much the more ſtrange, becauſe 'tis confidently reported that upon hearing the Papers ſo Charged, upon my Lord <hi>Preſton</hi> at his Tryal, he ſaid that Night publickly at the <hi>Grecian Coffee-houſe</hi> in <hi>Devereux-Court</hi> near the <hi>Middle Temple,</hi> that if he was not Excepted againſt upon Monday, he could not bring in either of the other; Guilty, in Relation to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; yet he it was that would have helped them to Evidence, and improv'd one Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation againſt Mr. <hi>Aſhton,</hi> which the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer I ſuppoſe had from the ſame <hi>Mint, viz.</hi> That one of the Papers was written in Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Hand; though, as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer obſerves, it had been very material to have made Proof of that upon his <hi>Tryal,</hi> which they might eaſily have done, had it been true; no Man's Hand being better known, and they having in their Hands Volumes of his Writing, when he was in Places at Court: Though it had been after all for the Honour of our <hi>Deliverers</hi> to have <hi>exploded Similitude of Hands</hi> from being Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Caſes of <hi>High Treaſon.</hi> And unleſs the Anſwerer proves the Delivery of it to a third Perſon, he will be thought as much the virulent and unjuſt Murtherers of his Reputation, as the others were of his Body, for want of due Proof that he knew the Contents. I think a Man is innocent of what he dies for, in the Sight of the Law, if the Evidence does not amount to Legal Proofs of the <hi>Indictment,</hi> and that ought in Common Juſtice as well as Charity to be thought the meaning of his <hi>Aſſerted</hi> Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency; for he does not pretend he had not endeavoured to Reſtore the Uncle, and the Father, of Him and Her that poſſeſs the Throne.</p>
            <p>§ 4 I don't ſee in Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Paper ſo much Art as Honeſty, according to his Principles; but I find in the Anſwerer all the advantage taken that his own ſix Weeks Labour, and a Club, could furniſh; from hence a Compliment Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi> makes the Court Fol. 112 and 115. is with him a Proof that Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi> had a Copy of the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>Pannel of the Jury, ſufficient notice,</hi> &amp;c. (which I believe, and always did, to be neceſſary to make a Tryal juſt and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, according to the Laws of <hi>England</hi>)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37443:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>at leaſt the ſtreſs this Anſwerer lays upon that Compliment, proves that he eſteems all the management of that Tryal to have been very fair, and that ſo <hi>Pol</hi>—'s <hi>Brats</hi> in the Charge is a Language well becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Judge, and that <hi>Herbert</hi>'s enſnaring Queſtions are no leſs becoming an impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Jury-man; I omit to mention any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hardſhips both in Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s and in my Lord <hi>Preſton</hi>'s <hi>Tryal,</hi> but particularly the King's Council's excepting againſt ſo many Jury-men without ſhewing Cauſe, which is ſo notorious a Prejudice to a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, that unleſs they can ſhew very <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Preſidents</hi> of the like Practice in Criminal Caſes, they muſt give me, and others, leave to think it one of the boldeſt Encroachments upon the People's Liberties that our Age has produc'd; and all good Men ought to reflect upon the great Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their Liberties in this caſe by ſuch unheard of Methods, as the late Tryals give us an Account of. The Council for the Crown in the Tryal of <hi>Croan</hi> excepting againſt Jury-men without ſhewing Cauſe, and not being publickly animadverted upon for ſo doing, it gave them confidence to do the ſame thing in my Lord <hi>Preſton</hi>'s Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; and had they had need, they would doubtleſs have ventured to ſet by Men, after they had been Sworn to paſs upon the Life of the Priſoner; as in <hi>Croan</hi>'s Tryal they ſet by Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> Goldſmith, Mr. <hi>Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> Tobacconiſt, Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> Herald Painter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all Men of Wealth, and Reputation; a procedure ſo palpably unjuſt, that my Lord <hi>Nott—m</hi> could not believe it, when it was told him.</p>
            <p>§ 5. Nor muſt I neglect to reiterate that unuſual way of Charging the <hi>Jury</hi> in theſe Tryals; the Bench often tells them that they believe in their Conſcience, that the Priſoners are Guilty of ſuch and ſuch a thing, and that they muſt bring in their Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, <hi>Guilty;</hi> now the <hi>Jury</hi> is to have no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief but what ariſes <hi>plainly</hi> and <hi>poſitively</hi> from the Evidence brought before them, their Conſciences are to be directed by plain Proof that appears ſo to them, not to be guided by other Men's Reaſons; and if their belief be determined any other ways, than from the Evidence before them, all Tryals will be rendred very Precarious; and I am very ſorry to ſee our <hi>Reformers</hi> out bid in this point all the Extravagancies of which they ſo much complain'd of. If theſe things are neceſſary to ſupport what is done, I will recommend farther to them the <hi>Scotch Boots</hi> and all the inventions of Tyranny in all Country's; but let us not pretend Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie for our Laws, and our Liberties, and encourage the moſt dangerous outrages againſt them. And God grant ſucceeding Times may never learn by their Example. God grant that a Judge may never dare to leave a matter of Law, as <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of <hi>hands</hi> was to a <hi>Jury;</hi> nor them to find matter of Fact but according to the Evidence produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; and may he grant likewiſe that it may be ſcandalous to the laſt Degree in a Jury-man to turn Proſecutor, and buſle for Evidence; had ſome of the Judges and Jury-men in the late Reigns been made Examples, we ſhould have found theſe more tender in this; but perhaps ſome Men were cautious in that, knowing they ſhould have occaſion to uſe the <hi>Preſidents</hi> in this. But I return to what more particularly concerns Mr. <hi>Aſhton the Man</hi> (as <hi>P.</hi> in his Charge calls him) who ought to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by every Party, if they have a fence of bravery in themſelves; it is a ſhame that thoſe that extolled the Gallantry of <hi>Sydney</hi> ſhould leſſen his Character, by ſaying
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37443:3"/>how eaſy it is for an Engliſh Man to dye; for few have, or can dye like Mr. <hi>Aſhton.</hi> Let us acknowledge <hi>Virtue</hi> in our Enemies, and have a greatneſs above <hi>Sect,</hi> above <hi>Mode</hi> and above <hi>Party;</hi> 'tis Engliſh Men come to this, they are not worthy of that liberty about which they make ſuch ado.</p>
            <p>§ 6. Thus much for Mr. <hi>Aſhton;</hi> I will now paſs to the conſideration to <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of this Cauſe, and the Legitimacy of the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The prevaricating Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> have ſo plainly contradicted, by their Practices all that they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Written; they have been all ſuch <hi>Sherlocks,</hi> that a Man had need be well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of his Religion to keep him from <hi>Hobbiſm.</hi> Let thoſe that Read this Pamphlet, Read the Authors Quoted in the <hi>Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience,</hi> let them peruſe <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s <hi>Letter to my Lord Ruſſel</hi> when he was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to dye. Let them conſider impartially what all of them would have had the World believe they meant at that time, and then if they can, let them forbear abhorring ſuch Practical Atheiſts, as are our <hi>Swearing ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired Divines.</hi> I blame them ſufficiently for Aſcribing ſuch Luſcious Authority to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they have tempted them to Exerciſe an uncontroleable <hi>Rule,</hi> and now they as vilely flatter the <hi>Mobb.</hi> I am not bound to defend all Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Principles, which they had taught him; but I am confident they would have been Orthodox with the Body of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> had the Declaration of Indulgence never been put out by King <hi>James;</hi> and whatever the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer ſaith pag. 9 and 10. though too many <hi>prevaricate</hi> by Submiſſion, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, yet there are but few of the Sons of that Church who ſubmit to the <hi>Pr. of Or.</hi> as, or believe him, the <hi>Rightful Lawful King,</hi> and ſo conſequently the Object of <hi>Paſſive Obedience;</hi> thoſe that were of that Church in both <hi>Houſes</hi> would have appeared as much againſt that Alteration of the Oath, as they did againſt <hi>Abjuration:</hi> Nay the very Secretary that is of that Communion, though he has gone greater lengths, than thoſe who are ſtrictly and ſincerely of that Principle can approve of, would not I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, be able to ſtretch his Conſcience to ſwear this an Elective Monarchy, or the Quarrel Juſt, or which is the ſame thing the <hi>Pr.</hi> of <hi>Or. Lawful Rightful King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 7. If the <hi>Prince of</hi> Orange<hi>'s Declaration</hi> had been purſued (which was once by Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi> deſigned to have been Re-prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a proof, how well it hath been made good) if the falſe ſteps of the late Reigns had been rectified; if the Objected <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, League,</hi> and <hi>Murther,</hi> had been proved; the ill Miniſters called to account, and the <hi>Prerogative</hi> fully debated and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> (<hi>a Reformation</hi> that would have lookt worth our <hi>Hazards,</hi> our <hi>Fortunes,</hi> our <hi>Reproach,</hi> and our <hi>Lives</hi>) I ſay if this had been the effect of the <hi>Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,</hi> it might have tempted a prudent Man to ſit quiet: But where are the <hi>Quo-Warranto-Projectors, the ſurrenderers</hi> of Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or the <hi>Regulators</hi> puniſhed? many of them are well, and well prefer'd. Is the <hi>Parliament Houſe</hi> leſs crouded with Officers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Danby</hi> is Preſident of the <hi>Council,</hi> and knows how to manage that matter. Are the Elections and returns better ſecured? The Quakers in the late Elections were no <hi>Freeholders</hi> in <hi>Barkſhire, Hartfordſhire,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Jack How</hi> was a better Churchman than <hi>Powle</hi> who was Speaker to the Convention upon the Corporation bottom at <hi>Windſor.</hi> Are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lives Liberties</hi> and the Eſtates of Englishmen better guarded? Unleſs you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37443:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>think mercenary Foreiners fitter for that purpoſe than ſuch who having Relations amongſt us would be, and were <hi>tite</hi> to the <hi>National Intereſt.</hi> I know nothing we are the better, or wiſer in, but in the Methos of Taxing the Subjects, and Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Pill</hi> with popular Names, Enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Martial Laws, Suſpence</hi> of the <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus, &amp;c.</hi> while thoſe very Perſons who had taught us, That the King could not be called to account by his Subjects, and both ſwore themſelves, and obliged others to ſwear, that it was not Lawful upon any pretence whatſoever to take Arms againſt him, engaged both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and others, to help the <hi>Pr.</hi> of <hi>Or.</hi> to dethrone his Uncle, and his Princeſſes Father, the Lord's Anointed, and their own Lawful and Rightful Sovereign. The Prince's <hi>Declaration,</hi> and the <hi>Memorial of the States,</hi> denied that this was his Deſign, but St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> has found it in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 8. Now give me leave to examine the Juſtice of this Engagement; the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer plainly points out, that it was to ſtop the Increaſe of the <hi>French Monarchy:</hi> But this will not go down till the <hi>French League</hi> is proved, the contrary of which was moſt true; inſomuch that though <hi>d' Avaux</hi> had got the Secret of this Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the <hi>King of France</hi> preſſed King <hi>James</hi> to take Care, yet he was jealous it was art in the <hi>French King</hi> to dip him in his <hi>Quarrel,</hi> and could not believe the <hi>P. of O.</hi> would undertake what he thought ſo horrid and unnatural: So that <hi>Van Cyters</hi> his falſe <hi>Proteſtations</hi> had more Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit than the true <hi>Informations</hi> of <hi>Barillion;</hi> and ſome will think it was not impoſſible for that Parliament which K. <hi>James</hi> was Calling, to have perſwaded him to have taken a juſt Care to ballance <hi>Europe:</hi> I am far from commending the way they were to be Choſen in, perhaps I am as nice as any Man living of the <hi>Privileges of Engliſh-men,</hi> but I believe the Men that were recommended to the <hi>Corporations</hi> were many of them Choſen into the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,</hi> and ſome of them perhaps were but too hot Members there; nor do I believe they could have been mealy-mouth'd under <hi>King James:</hi> So that the Emiſſaries of the <hi>P. of O.</hi> might have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded them to talk loudly of the <hi>Growth of France,</hi> and of the <hi>Growth of Popery,</hi> without all that Expence of Blood and Treaſure we have been at, and God knows when it will be at an End; though if he came to ſave the People of <hi>England,</hi> he ſhould have made us the better for his Preferment, and our Redemption; but conſidering the <hi>Natural Obligations</hi> he had to King <hi>James,</hi> he ſhould not have made him only the worſe.</p>
            <p>§ 9. And here I cannot forbear men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning one thing that is mightily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd, <hi>viz.</hi> that he did not only <hi>dethrone</hi> him as a <hi>King</hi> but deſpoiled him as a Merchant; and that when Sir <hi>Robert Howard</hi> denied by the <hi>Pr.</hi> of <hi>Or.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to let him have his own Money out of his own Exchequer, after he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and he was forced to borrow of a faithful Servant a Sum of Money to carry him off, and out of his great Juſtice made over to that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſome Money which he had in the <hi>Eaſt-India-Company</hi> (as a Trader) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inburſe him, (the Company willingly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37443:4"/>joyning in the diſpoſal) yet even here he is uſing all his Power to wreſt this Money out of the Gentleman's hands and ſuffers all the Tradeſmen to whom the diſpoſſeſſed <hi>King</hi> was indebted to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that Gentleman for what belongs to the <hi>Royal Treaſury to ſatisfy;</hi> he ought to give greater encouragement to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, for <hi>Jeffrys</hi> himſelf could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail to deſtroy one of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi>'s menial Servants after his defeat; and this preſent <hi>King</hi> ſhould be aſhamed to be hardeſt upon ſuch as Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi> and this Gentleman were, and to ſuffer all <hi>his Courts</hi> (and to help them too) to worry them every <hi>Term.</hi> This makes Mankind wonder.</p>
            <p>§ 10. But to return to the <hi>Invading Politicks; The Dutch Ambaſſador</hi> ought not to have been ordered to deny thoſe Preparations were againſt King <hi>James;</hi> and it was fit to have tryed whether things might not have been amicable ſet right by <hi>Treaty,</hi> before they entered into <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> and <hi>Clandeſtine Confederacies;</hi> with the Pope, the Emperor, and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh King (with the Aſſiſtance of the Inquiſition) to Eſtabliſh the true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion. Nor ſhould <hi>Dickvelt</hi> have come hither to corrupt and to Liſt the <hi>King's</hi> Subjects againſt him. Thoſe that can find Preſidents and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for theſe things, can Reverſe <hi>Nature</hi> and all her Laws, can put off the ſence of a God and a World to come, whilſt they baſely lend their <hi>Pens,</hi> to the blackeſt Villanies; they may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim for <hi>Lucifer,</hi> and commend the Aſpiring minds of the fallen <hi>Angels,</hi> who have obtained a Government and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendency</hi> over Perjur'd and Wretched Souls, <hi>over</hi> the Baſe, the Treacherous, and the Ungrateful, and reign in the Hearts of none elſe; and that Church. Divine that can make the <hi>Meſſage</hi> by the <hi>Three Noble Lords,</hi> a very good natur'd Compliment may go a great way, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards proving the <hi>Regicides</hi> Noble, and Conſciencious Patriots; I think in my Conſcience by his wording that <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph</hi> (which I had almoſt ſlipped over) he could have been willing, the Life of his Soveraign ſhould have been taken away, to put an end to the <hi>War</hi> and the <hi>Charge;</hi> he might have had Arguments from the <hi>Army Remonſtrants</hi> 1648. And with Dr. <hi>Bur—t</hi>'s help and from his Text have proved <hi>it the Lord's doing;</hi> a Man would think he had been in <hi>Holland,</hi> that he allows all things to be done for Intereſt, and the moſt unnatural barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to be good breeding if it does the buſineſs; <hi>he</hi> lets looſe all the Ambition imaginable in Princes againſt all the Sacred Ties of <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, againſt their <hi>Uncles,</hi> their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> their <hi>Allies,</hi> their <hi>Friends,</hi> and their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers-in-Law;</hi> and ſets down the wildeſt <hi>Maxims</hi> that were ever Advanced in <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> and thinks to caſt upon the <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> every <hi>Act of State</hi> wherein Princes have conſulted their own ſecular Advantages, and got a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Clergy, or perhaps but one of that <hi>Robe</hi> to Countenance what yet was not ſo apparently oppoſite to the ſence of all good Men, as our Pretences are.</p>
            <p>For my part this Anſwerer ſhall no more ſend me to the <hi>French</hi> Cabinet than to the <hi>Netherlands</hi> to be inſtructed in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37443:4"/>And I know no body that would have blamed the <hi>Pr.</hi> of <hi>Or.</hi> for obſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>French Deſigns,</hi> if he had not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken an unjuſt way to do it. I wiſh he could have reſettled the Edicts of <hi>Nantes,</hi> and the Aſſembly of the States there, the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Oppreſſed,</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> but I am ſorry he has choſen rather to be what <hi>After-ages</hi> will call a <hi>Pirate,</hi> and a <hi>Robber,</hi> than to be the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged <hi>Benefactor</hi> and <hi>Protector</hi> of Mankind. He has had great Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, but he has ſhown he knows not how to uſe them. He has not a Soul large enough for the <hi>Poſt</hi> in which this fickle Nation has put him. A Paultry <hi>Self-Intereſt</hi> governs his <hi>Councils,</hi> and as ill Men govern him, and make him miſtake his way to <hi>Glory;</hi> there were too appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Prints of this <hi>Self-Intereſt,</hi> in that part of his <hi>Declaration</hi> quoted by this <hi>Anſwerer</hi> in relation to the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales;</hi> and ſince that is a new inſiſted on by this <hi>Licenſed Author</hi> (though the <hi>Convention</hi> and <hi>preſent Parliament</hi> wiſely let it alone, becauſe many of the <hi>Members</hi> knew there would be produced <hi>unanſwerable</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Proofs</hi>) I will promiſe them they ſhall hear of it with a Witneſs in a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Diſcourſe,</hi> ſince it would draw this Paper to too great a length. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, after I have ſolemnly returned my Thanks to the Government, for at <hi>laſt</hi> publiſhing Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Speech, though not without the beſt <hi>Anſwer</hi> they could make to it, which yet ſcarce ever was bought, but to make the <hi>Speech</hi> in a Cloſet no <hi>Crime.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>The Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>SInce this went to the Preſs there is publiſhed part of what Mr. <hi>Aſhton</hi> left in the Hands of a private Friend; I hear the Court is much Enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at it, and there is much hunting after the <hi>Printer:</hi> It ſeems the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is very tender about the Proof of the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> Mankind muſt be informed in that Matter; and thoſe that believe <hi>he</hi> is Legitimate only deſire the next Parliament will give them a Fair Hearing. And if they don't demonſtrate <hi>him</hi> ſo, by all the Series of Proofs neceſſary in ſuch a Caſe, and to the Satisfaction of the whole World, they will be content to ſubmit to, and to joyn, even with the Abdication, Conqueſt, or any other Title the King <hi>de Facto</hi> likes beſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
